Okay.
uh little bit more that I forgot to say
about the five houses and then
uh I'll tell you something
cool in the gishi course which is 25
years hard years hard debating hard work
uh we don't study diamond way even one
sentence
uh we don't study diamond way uh if you
finish the gishi course. You allowed to
go to the diamond way course. Uh so very
few people go to the diamond way
monastery. There's only two, Gume and
GU. My teacher was the vice president of
Gume. So anyway,
uh there's no Diamond Way material in
the whole Gishi course, okay?
But there's a tradition that lam rim
steps of the path course
uh you teach a little taste of diamond
way at the
end. You
understand?
Okay. So, we're going to do a little
taste uh at the end. Okay.
today. Uh just to give you the taste.
Okay. Actually, I gave you the real
taste already at the New York
restaurant. Uh that's the real taste. Um
one more thing about the
five
houses.
Um my dream is 10
houses. Uh my real dream is 10 houses.
Uh and why I say 10 houses? So we have a
classic house we which is to become a
teacher of the 18 courses foundation
courses. Then we have samadei house
which is to be to become a real
meditation teacher. Okay. Then we have
mountain house. I want to be a teacher
to teach people to be in retreat. How to
do retreat. What's the next one?
stairway house, staircase house, which
means I want to teach
people style. Okay. Lim style. It's a
different style. It's less difficult and
it's kind of more fun than the classics.
I prefer the classics personally. Uh and
then diamond house, diamond way house.
Okay. And I have a dream. You see you
can teach like tomorrow morning we have
a uh translator class right many people
will disappear tomorrow morning
uh and because those classes are
difficult okay and and there are I don't
know people get tired they are they are
difficult I like to
teach translator way all the books I
ever taught I always teach from the
ancient book. You people who came to my
classes for many years, I always like to
teach from the ancient books directly
and I think that's very important. Uh
traditional Buddhism, that's real
Buddhism. Okay, those classes,
translator class, that's real Buddhism.
I there's many strange Buddhisms in the
world. that what we teach in the
translator class is real classical
Buddhism in two and a half thousand
years and it's pure. It's completely
pure and it's it's unbelievable. But
it's not for everybody. Uh only some
people enjoy it. So other people can't
study like that. They're not Oh, stop
that. Who is that? Just in case it's my
boss. No.
uh not everybody can study that
way. And so in my lifetime
uh
[Music]
I I always taught both ways. Okay? I
always taught both ways. So you know
sometimes I teach business people and I
don't mention Buddhism. I never mention
Buddha. I don't I don't even mention
Buddhism. I'll tell you a secret.
If a person
understands seeds well, okay, if a
person really understands seeds,
uh, and if they have some training in
emptiness, they're Buddhist. That's a
definition. Okay? They are
Buddhist. Okay? That's a definition of
Buddhist. And then uh if they don't
understand seeds and they don't
understand emptiness and their
grandmother was a Buddhist and their
mother was a Buddhist and they go to
temple every day, they are not a
Buddhist. Okay. I think it's fun to
teach the business people seeds and
emptiness then they are the real
British understand but they don't
know. I think it's fun. Uh all these New
York business guys are Buddhist and they
don't know and then all these other
people their grandmother and their
mother and they go to temple and they're
not Buddhist. Okay, understand what I
mean to say is
uh you can teach the same
truth religious way and you can teach it
non-religious way and I think they are
both valuable. Both are valuable. I
think uh some people they should learn
Buddhism religious way. they they can go
to the temple and they can do
prostrations and and all this thing they
can do and that's beautiful and that's a
good thing and then some people prefer
to to practice their Buddhism in in the
business office you know and and they
are also doing good pure Buddhism if
they understand seeds and they
understand emptiness they are Buddhist
so I I love to teach both so DCI
business people
ACI people want to do Buddhism.
Okay. I like to have both. I like to
make both of them
available to people. Why? Cuz some
people like business way and some people
like temple
way. And we want to help everybody. We
want to give everybody some chance to to
be happy. So we don't say you have
to you have to wear a red robe or or you
have to shave your head or you have to
go money baby home. Uh that's good.
That's okay. Some people it's good for
them. Some people look I just want to
have a family. I just want to do my work
and I want to do Buddhism this way. Then
you should have both option I think.
Okay. And I always thought that way my
whole life I taught this way. And uh and
I'm happy. I'm very happy uh with the
result.
Therefore, we will split the five houses
from bottom to
top. Okay. Here's the five houses
for people who want to do Buddhism
way. And here's the five houses for
people who they just want to do it like
business way or not religious way. They
want to do it without all the religion.
Okay. I think if you're going to help
the people in the
world, split the five houses in the
middle. And so there will be a classics
house ancient book classics house. And
then there'll be a modern classic house.
And then what's the second one?
There'll be somati house for Buddhist
people and somati house for normal
people. Then there'll be
a mountain retreat for Buddhist people
and retreat for people who just want to
learn to do retreat and like that every
house I want to split the houses uh this
way. So now uh Tim used
to have the
trouble to run one
organization and now he has the trouble
to run 11
organization because it's five times two
plus the old ACI right
so his head going to become like mine
and John Brady
uh already something happening
So I have I you know I have an idea he
needs to hire some more people I think.
So he cannot he will have a breakdown if
he does it himself. And I think in the
last year I know him personally. Uh he
worked too hard. He he he will get sick.
He will hurt himself. And my
responsibility is to make sure the
directors are overworked but not sick.
Right. So, uh I think he needs some he's
going to need some
help. So, you know, three ideas. Number
one, if you would like to get
involved with the creation of the five
houses, which is really 10 houses, you
understand? It needs more people.
Uh then then please uh talk to Tim. Do
you have a QR code? No. Just he has a QR
code here. Uh talk to him. Don't be shy.
You know you're going home uh after
tomorrow or something. Think about it.
Okay. If you have some time and if you
are capable person, if you would like to
be in I think it's fun. I started the
diamond
business when we had three
diamonds and we had three people. Later
we had 10,000 people and we did 300,000
diamonds a day. Okay. And I got there on
the first day and that was cool. You
know, they have to take me cuz there's
nobody else. Uh that's how I became vice
president. So what I mean is uh if you
can be there on the first day, if you
can be involved on the first day, I
think it's cool. Okay. And uh so if
you're
interested to
help run the the 10 10 houses, right? 10
11 then talk to Tim. Okay? And and then
that leads me to my last subject. I have
to pay all these people. Okay? In the
end, why I'm the big
grandpa is not because everyone loved
me. It's because I'm a good
fundraiser. Okay? So, you know, we have
organizations. Every time they run out
of money, they knock on my house
door. Can you please fundra for us? You
know, I'm like,
okay. You know, then I have to do, you
know, and I'm happy to do it, you know.
I I I'm happy to do it and I do it every
day and uh I'm very happy to do it. But
I it it would if if we're going to hire
more people, if more people going to
work for the 10 houses, the five house,
we call it five houses, okay? Uh I need
more fundraising. I need to raise more
money. And it's on me. It always comes
down to me and I'm happy to do it. Uh so
I'm going to do it right now.
Okay. Uh I'm going to the start of the
diamond way
uh teaching at the end of this lum room.
Okay. And I never taught it to
anybody.
Uh so here we go. Uh it's tradition
uh to to teach it at the end of a long
room
uh session. Hang on.
[Music]
Oh, I told you the wrong thing wrong.
Let me
[Music]
see. Hang on. I wasn't expecting to do
this. So,
what's the first sentence say?
Neither can I. No, he's not in the right
place.
Yeah.
20 23rd. So maybe
near. Okay.
Okay. Good. All
right. You sure,
Tim? Hang on.
Yeah, good. Okay, here we go. Uh, this
is the 23rd day of the original
teaching. Okay, which happened in 1921,
something like
that. My teacher was there, by the way.
And this was his teacher. My Do you want
to hear a cute story? My teacher was a
bad boy. And uh when he joined the
monastery he was 7 years old and he was
a very bad student and he very bad
behavior. His favorite activity in the
monastery in the in those monasteries
inside the monastery you not allowed to
wear
shoes. So his favorite activity is to
spread thumbtacks everywhere.
understand then the monk will step on
them and ah and he have so much fun like
that. So anyway, he was a very bad boy
and uh he
went he got a job. Uh they said uh you
can be nerpa nerpa means you have to do
the
refreshments for the big teaching. Okay,
it means you can't even go in the
teaching. You spend the whole hour
outside making refreshments for people.
He's he's called
nerpa. I understand it because I used to
be the nera also for my teacher. So I'm
always cooking. When the high llamas
come, I never get to meet them cuz I'm
cooking. And uh anyway, he he will do
the cooking. And then the great grade
teachers, they know that nerpa is
suffering in the kitchen and they will
go to the kitchen first.
uh before the teaching and they will
talk to the workers and it's very sweet.
Uh they will give them a teaching in the
kitchen
uh cuz they know these people have to
work the whole time. They can't come to
the teaching you know so they will go to
the kitchen and my teacher was in the
kitchen. My granddaughter does
that.
Uh anyway,
uh Paboner, the author of the L room,
came into
the We have a Do you have a picture? The
last picture, Francisco, maybe. I don't
know. Those three teachers. I don't know
if you have it. See if you can find it.
It's black and white. Yeah.
Nice. Okay.
Uh on the left is Pabona Reach who who
wrote this book.
Okay. And then in the middle is Tri
who's my teacher's direct
teacher. He wrote this book down. Okay.
He was sitting in the audience. Pabonga
didn't write the book down. Pabonga
taught the book. Then Cha wrote the book
down. and he spent 20 years cleaning it
up. He's very similar to Bo and
Jamie. Okay. After the teaching
finished, he cleaned it up for over 15
years. And uh that book which the middle
teacher created which is what you
studied, it is the greatest book in the
Tibetan language. Easily I can say that.
Okay. in 1,000 years. It's the greatest
book. It's the most amazing book. Okay.
Which you just
finished. Okay. So, he's the we we
we should be grateful to those two. Then
on this side is uh my
teacher. He never
wears he never don't wear his
robes ever.
Uh but he has to take a passport
picture and uh the guy told him you have
to wear something normal for so we put
on
this western clothes and uh I love that
picture. I that's very
cool. So that's my favorite picture. So
he taught it to me for 30 years and uh
those are the three great teachers of
this text.
Okay. Uh and they're also the three
great teachers of diamond way. Okay. Uh
when we study diamond way uh we will
study uh the diamond way teachings of
these three teachers and they're the
greatest in my opinion uh diamond way
teachers in the last 100 years 200
years. Okay. These are the real holders
of the diamond way teachings and we will
study their teachings. Okay.
Uh, okay. So, here we go. For good luck.
Okay. Uh, just to put your toe in the
Diamond Way swimming pool.
Oh, sorry. I forgot to finish the story.
Uh, can we do the picture one more time?
I'm sorry.
Uh so this
teacher went to the kitchen
uh to give a small blessing and teaching
to the cooks basically and my teacher
was there because he's the worst
student and uh and Pabok grab his
head and he's
like and then he says this one's going
to be great, you know, but and my
teacher is
like and then
uh after that he he became a highest
gushi and uh he
debate uh
5,000 monks and he's number
one okay he's number one gay and
uh so anyway That's the story of uh how
this book got to you cuz my teacher hit
me. Okay. All right. Here we go. Uh
we'll do a little bit uh for good luck.
Okay. We have about 20 minutes. Let's
see how far we can do go. Okay.
And it's considered uh
traditional. At the end of a 14-year
teaching or something, you give a like
half hour of diamond way from the book.
It's from the end of the book. Okay? And
it's just to put a seed in your mind for
the for the next few years. Okay? All
right. And I'll just read it. Okay.
On the 23rd day of the
[Music]
teaching there's a famous quotation from
the king of the
dharma which is
uh he this
teacher he
uh quote the three principle path. Okay.
Lo very famous short l
actually and he gave a lung means uh
oral reading of the book.
Okay. Before uh they teach the diamond
way they make sure people have the right
motivation. Okay. And the right
motivation is
uh I'm I'm sad to see this world
uh where yesterday somebody shot uh a
famous businessman in New York City on
the street. They just went up and shoot
him, you know, kill him. They're not a
criminal. They are just some guy. And uh
I'm sorry to live in a world where
people just walk up to you and kill you
on the street. You know, he has two
children. He's nice guy. U I I I
I want to see a better world. I want to
make this a better world. I don't want
to stay in a world where people kill
each other. I don't I don't like it.
Okay.
So he got us ready our
motivation. Then
he went over the t
the outline that he taught the day
before which is tradition.
Uh
uh now it's a very strange sentence
because
uh when you say I want to tell you
something you
say means I'll tell you something.
But in Tibetan language there's a high
language when you talk to your teacher.
So you use different words and you use
different language. It's a completely
separate language and you use very very
uh
high words you know
like oh honorable teacher I would you
know may I please say something to you
you know like this very polite okay and
uh he says here I reached part three of
the whole book the whole book is 800
pages
394 folios something like that 800 pages
okay in English that is uh over 6,000
pages okay and he said okay we reached
the last part okay take bala and we
reached the last part and then
congratulations because we all survive
for 14 years that's
unusual usually some people disappear
okay all right
Then he says, "I would like to offer you
an
explanation of the beginning of the
diamond ring." Okay? And he uses shu. So
for me, it's very important. Shu means
uh when you're talking to a high
teacher. You see what I mean? It's the
word for I would like to tell you
something. But if you use this verb, it
means that person is like almost like a
Buddha. You know
understand the teacher is talking to the
students after 23 days of teaching and
he says
shuna may I say something? You see what
I mean? It means he's already see the
audience. Maybe there's some Buddhas in
the audience. Maybe some of these
students are fake
student. Maybe they are
disguised. Uh Buddha in disguise.
Okay. Especially the irritating
ones. Okay. Maybe they are testing us.
Okay. Got it. It's very important that
he used the verb
shun means may
I speak to your honorable high self
about the diamond wave. Okay. All right.
That's just the beginning.
[Music]
Okay. We already went through the steps
of the path for beginning level.
And then we went to the steps of the
path for medium
level. And I was teaching you during
those
sections about
ninjun means uh wake up about life. You
know wake up. You know how many people
have to die around you before you
understand you have to die. You are next
in line. Okay. Oh, my grandma my great
grandma died when I was born. Okay. Then
my grandma died when I was a kid. Oh,
okay. Then my mom died when I was about
20. Yeah. Then then what? Duh. Who's
next? Okay. You don't need any other
Buddhism. You don't need any other
logic. You know, my great grandmother
died when I was born. My I never met my
grandfather, for example. He died when I
was three or something. Then my father
died, then my mother
died. Who's next? You know, we're all
just in line. If you think you're not in
line, you're
really crazy. Okay, you are in line and
you're next in line. Okay, so you got to
get ready.
Okay. Well, guess what? I have to I
couldn't come to the last class. Why I
have to pack to fly home tomorrow? Will
the plane leave
tomorrow? Not sure. Especially if you're
in America, they delay every second
flight. Uh do you have to
die? 100% yes. Then pack that bag first,
then pack for your house. You know, pack
the other bag. That one's for sure. They
don't cancel that one. Okay. And they
don't give you a
refund. Okay. Same as the other
airlines. Okay. Shuna. So he I taught
you all that you are next in line. Okay.
Take take care of your pack for the next
life now then enjoy the rest of your
life. Okay? That's a smart thing. Don't
wait till the end of your life. Okay?
Sometimes you don't have time. Sometimes
you get run over by one of those cute
little Japanese cars. All right. In
Kyoto before you go
home, then I taught you guys about way
of life. How to
live by taking care of other people. And
you know right now you when I say other
people you think about your family or
you think about your friends or thinking
like that. Okay. When you get to be a
bodhis
sappa other people
means countless billions of planets and
you have the power you have
the you yourself have the
power to take care of billions and
billions and billions of planets. Okay,
it's nice to have planets in your
pocket. Yeah, I'll go to that one. Take
care of everybody. Then I'll switch the
other one before
breakfast. That's how they think like
that. Okay. All right. That's
bodhisappa. That's real bodhisappa.
Okay. Once we got into the mood of
bodhis, I taught you guys about
emptiness. Then I I I we went through
the teachings on emptiness, the pen.
[Music]
Okay. Once you have this
background in the steps of the path,
it's time to enter
uh the diamond way. It's time to enter
diamond way. Okay. Yay. After 14 years,
you reached it.
Y if you try to enter diamond way
without
studying steps of the
pathsu mandola you cannot get to
Buddhahood it will it won't work it's
not possible Okay, you you can you know
sneak in the back of Diamond Way
house but it doesn't work. Okay, you
know you you will not help you. Okay,
you need to be
prepared.
Okay, 14 years is enough. One year is
enough. Okay, next year
If you put a two-year-old kid on top of
a wild
horse means
uh means it's not going to help the kid
and on top of
that it's dangerous. Okay, put a kid on
top of a wild horse. No saddle. Let let
him go. You might kill the child. Okay,
it's
irresponsible, you know. Hey, we got a
new super Tesla car. What's that?
Xiaomi. Show me. Show me. Xiaomi. I want
one of those. Uh, okay. Yeah. Okay.
Super Xiaomi car, you know. You know,
and then put it put my granddaughter,
two years old, put her in the car. Okay,
honey. Push the gas. Good luck. Close
the door. You're just going to hurt her.
She'll kill
herself. You You know where he's going,
right?
So, it's dangerous and
irresponsible to put a 2-year-old in a
powerful car car called Diamond
Way. Okay. 2-year-old means someone who
didn't get proper Lim teachings.
[Music]
Okay. Your
kid. Yes, it's true that Diamond Way is
a lot faster, but
uh
uh but can they have to be well trained
to use the speed to get the benefit of
the speed of the new car? They have to
or the crazy horse. Okay.
Uh, the appearance of diamond way on a
planet is more rare than the appearance
of a Buddha on a planet.
The appearance of diamond weight
teachings on a planet is more rare than
the appearance of a Buddha on a planet
because not every
Buddha teaches the diamond way. Okay.
But if you get a chance to study uh
diamond way, then even in a in
a even in a terrible
planet where the life is only 70, 80
years old, you can easily reach
Buddhahood. Okay? In one life, you can
easily reach Buddhahood. This is
considered
a like
uh refugee planet or
something. In English we say uh the bad
kids sit in the back of the
class. Do you have that in your in your
country?
Malaysia. The bad children sit in the
back of the class.
Yeah. This whole planet is bad children
from the back of the
class. Okay. The other planet already
became Buddha. We are the stupid of the
stupid. We born here. Okay. This is
called the back of the class planet in
in Buddhism.
Okay. Topa. But even those people if
they study diamond way they can become
Buddha in one life. Okay. Before they
die. Therefore, it's cool and amazing if
you can study diamond way in this life.
Okay. Cool and amazing. Look
good. I think you should a lot of people
they get cancer. Yesterday someone wrote
me. She came to class for a while. She
quit coming to class
for 15 years or something. Now she wrote
me this this morning. I have it right
here. She said, "I have now I got breast
cancer. Can I can you help me?" And I'm
I'm like I wrote her a long email. Of
course I'll help you. You know, I'll do
what I can. just she's going to meet me
at Peach Tree Cafe. She's going to come
from another
state to talk to me for 10 minutes at at
Peach Tree Cafe. But really, I've taught
Ram for 14 years and she didn't come.
You see what I mean? So, uh what can I
do in 10 minutes at Peach Tree Cafe? I
don't know. But, uh I'm okay. I I can do
this. So he says here
uh you know you can get a short-term
problem with your health or your life
and then suddenly you got very serious
about your Buddhism but I cannot teach
you in in 10 minutes 14 years I if I
could do that we could just teach for 10
minutes and then 13 years we can go to
dinner a good sushi
restaurant. If I try to tell you the
wannab wannabe
joke again, tell tell me to
stop. You told us twice already.
Okay. If you didn't hear about it, let
me
[Music]
know. Not a good idea.
Okay. Uh diamond way is not an emergency
vow at the end of your life. It's not
something you do after you get breast
cancer. It's something you do before you
get breast cancer. Okay? Then you don't
get breast cancer or something like
that. Okay? All
right. So the proper
uh way to do secret way diamond way is
to find a teacher correct teacher. Bun.
Bun means vajger charter. Someone who
can teach you diamond way.
Okay. Demba. Okay. Sen means
uh they should know what they're doing.
Okay.
Uh, I went to
uh I had to have this operation, you
know, and so I asked the doctor, my
doctor, my regular doctor, and I said,
she says, you need someone to surgery.
You need to have surgery. And I said,
who's who is there? She said well you
know you couple of doctors in this city
can uh do the surgery you know and I
checked them and I think I rather die
than go to those doctor I checked them I
live in a very small town all the
doctors where I live are drunk or
something I don't know so I'm
like know I'm not going to risk uh my
life. So, I flew to another state. I
went to California and I I found a good
doctor in uh in another city, you know.
And that's the same with Diamond Way,
okay? You don't go to a person who
doesn't know what they're doing for
diamond weight teaching because it's
like going to a surgeon who who's going
to the the surgeon in Arizona near
me, he's got famous for cutting the
wrong thing.
[Laughter]
And this other guy uh in California,
he's got a robot, you know, and you
know, I'm like, hm. And it the cut is
very small. You know, when I talk about
it, it looks very big, but uh he he
knows a special
way to uh do the surgery quickly and
without trouble.
And then you know the next day I was
translating in the bed you know and in
the morning I was working. So um in the
the big thing here the big first part of
the diamond way is very clear and that's
the last thing I'll say to you in 14
years. Okay. Find a find a real teacher.
Find someone who knows what the what
they're doing. Okay. Don't don't trust
your
body to some Arizona guy with a steak
knife. Like find find a good surgeon.
Find someone who knows uh who had good
training, okay? And and knows how to do
it properly. And don't don't think you
by the way just cuz they ring a bell or
they have a big hat or you know that's
actually lower tantra. Okay. the big
hat, the bell, all this stuff. I have
one. It's got a lot of dust on it. Uh,
and I know how to do it. I have all
those things. But,
uh, don't judge from that, you know,
judge judge judge who who can really
help you, who has the training. Okay?
Don't look at the clothes and
the Okay. Uh, check the person
carefully. spend some time. You You
don't know how many hours I spent online
to find a good surgeon, you know? I'm
not going to go to some guy next door,
you know. I'm going to find the best
one. I found the best one. I think he's
the best one maybe in the US or
something. And u it's worth it. Okay.
And I I will do it that way. If I'm
going to risk my life,
uh I'll I'll choose a good one. And you
should do the same.
In diamond way, you should do the same
thing. Okay? Be
careful. Be picky. Okay? Check the
person over and over and over. Okay?
Make sure they have training. Make sure
they know what they're talking about.
Okay? That's the
first class of diamond way. Okay? Thank
you. Okay.